George Ord Collection 1831-1864 Mss.B.Or2
American Philosophical Society
George Ord Collection
1831-1864
Mss.B.Or2
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
George Ord made important contributions as an ornithologist and writer but is also famous for his contempt of fellow ornithologist John James Audubon. Throughout his life he published numerous scientific articles and assisted in completing Alexander Wilson's life's work, American Ornithology; or, The Natural History of the Birds of the United States. Ord also left his mark as a member of the American Philosophical Society and as the president of the Academy of Natural Science of Philadelphia. The George Ord collection consists primarily of outgoing personal correspondence to Charles Waterton ranging from 1831 to 1866 that highlights Ord's professional as well as personal affairs, most notably his hostility toward Audubon. The collection is supplemented by correspondence of Ord's to and from various individuals regarding personal and business matters.
0.25 linear feet
Ord, George, 1781-1866
Box 1
Biographical/Historical note
George Ord (1781-1866, APS 1817) was a naturalist, ornithologist, and writer. He completed the eighth and ninth volumes of Alexander Wilson’s American Ornithology after Wilson’s death, and he described and formally named several of the specimens returned by the Lewis and Clark expedition. However, Ord is perhaps best known for his animosity towards ornithologist John James Audubon (1785-1851, APS 1831).
Ord was born in 1781 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. His father George Ord, a retired sea captain, was a ship chandler and rope maker. His mother was Rebecca Lindemeyer. Ord joined his father in his business in 1800 and continued in the business after his father's death in 1806. He retired in 1829, wealthy enough to allow him a comfortable life devoted to the pursuit of his scholarly interests. While there is no reliable record of his early formal education, he evidently became interested in the study of science and literature at a young age. In 1804 Ord married Margaret Biays, daughter of the Baltimore rope maker and shipbuilder Joseph Biays. Before Margaret died in 1808, the couple had two children, only one of whom survived to adulthood. Ord apparently remarried; however, information about this marriage is lacking.
Shortly after his first marriage, Ord made the acquaintance of the Scottish poet and naturalist Alexander Wilson (1766-1813, APS 1813), who had lived in Pennsylvania since 1794. The two men became close friends, and Ord accompanied Wilson on some of his expeditions around Philadelphia and New Jersey. When Wilson died in 1813, Ord was left to finish the final two volumes of Wilson's illustrated nine-volume American Ornithology.
Ord contributed numerous articles that appeared in the scientific periodicals of the day, including the British Annals and Magazine of Natural History, the Transactions of the American Philosophical Society, and the Journal of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia. His essay on American zoology in William Guthrie’s New Geographical and Commercial Grammar (1815) imposed, for the first time, binomial scientific names on several species of American birds and mammals. In this “first systematic Zoology of America by an American,” Ord described several of the specimens from the Lewis and Clark Expedition that Meriwether Lewis had deposited at Peale’s Museum at Thomas Jefferson’s behest. Moreover, Ord was able to draw on information furnished by Henry Brackenridge that came from the journals of Lewis and Clark. Ord eventually wrote the first scientific taxonomies of ten specimens returned by the expedition, more than any other individual. They included the black-tailed prairie dog ( Arctomys ludoviciana) and Ursus horribilis, better known as the grizzly bear.
Ord himself undertook only one extended scientific expedition. In 1817 he joined Thomas Say (1787-1834, APS 1817) and Titian Ramsey Peale (1799-1885, APS 1833) on a trip led by William Maclure (1763-1840) and funded by the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia to collect specimens in Georgia and Florida. The “Florida Party,” as the group was frequently called in Academy records, undertook what would be the first private, museum sponsored exploration in the United States. The aim was to collect specimens, make them available for study, and publicize the findings in lectures and the Academy’s new journal. The Academy hoped that this would put the institution on par with its European counterparts.
In addition to his interest in the natural sciences, Ord also had a passion for literature and philology. This is reflected in the assistance he gave to Noah Webster (1758-1843, APS 1827) in the completion of his dictionary. In addition, Robert Gordon Latham used an extensive manuscript completed by Ord in his revision of Samuel Johnson’s dictionary in 1870. Ord also wrote biographies of fellow naturalists Thomas Say and Charles A. Lesueur.
Despite these publications, Ord is mostly remembered for his less than friendly relationship with John James Audubon. In fact, Ord detested Audubon, calling him a "impudent pretender" and "neither a scholar nor philosopher." He described Audubon's book Birds of America as "stupid" and thought that his illustrations were "vile." After Audubon's death, Ord wrote that he believed his autobiography was a "fable" and that "little reliance can be placed on his [Audubon's] narrative." Audubon was not the only ornithologist to receive harsh words from Ord. Ord once wrote that the botanist and naturalist Thomas Nuttall was a "presumptuous ass" who deserved the "lash." Ord was known for his unkind words and strong opinions. His efforts to discredit Audubon in particular may have stemmed from his desire to preserve the claim to preeminence for Wilson. Indeed, Ord published a tribute to his late friend and mentor, titled Sketch of the Life of Alexander Wilson, in 1828, just when Audubon was beginning to publish his Birds of America.
Ord’s scientific contributions were widely recognized. In 1815 he became a member of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, serving as curator of their collections (1815-1817), vice-president (1816-1834), and on their publications committee (1817-1821, 1832, 1833). In 1817 he was elected a member of the American Philosophical Society, serving as secretary (1820-1827), vice president (1832-1835), councilor (1839), treasurer (1842-1847), and librarian (1842-1848). He was also a member of the Linnaean Society of London. He was president of the ANS from 1851 to 1858, a position that he "never sought after." He accepted the election despite of his age and "infirmities," and his "habits of retirement," which had rendered him "averse to company and the turmoil of life." In his later life he plunged further into the life of a recluse with each passing year. His health was not always good; he suffered from poor eyesight and regular bouts of influenza. He died in 1866 in Philadelphia and is buried in Philadelphia next to his friend and mentor Alexander Wilson.
Scope and Contents note
The George Ord Collection is a significant resource for the study of the life of George Ord, an important figure in the field of ornithology during the 19th century. The collection is primarily comprised of outgoing correspondence from Ord to Charles Waterton between 1831 and 1864, regarding fellow ornithologists, Ord's everyday activities, and his personal affairs. Letters by Ord and from various individuals, including Titian Ramsay Peale, who struggled with his career after the 1848-52 Wilkes expedition, are also part of the collection. This collection clearly draws a picture of Ord's personality as an outspoken, opinionated individual.
Ord's animosity towards John James Audubon is well represented throughout the collection. He calls Audubon an "impudent pretender" and his book "stupid" (23 April 1832). He complains that Audubon was a fake and unworthy of the high esteem that he received as an ornithologist from colleagues, contests numerous aspects of Audubon's writings and detests his drawings. His close personal relationship with Waterton is also illustrated in this collection. Through his correspondence with Waterton a clear picture is drawn of his close but at times distant relationship with Charles Lucien Bonaparte, an influential ornithologist and nephew of Napoleon Bonaparte. Other natural scientists who experienced Ord's critical opinion included Thomas Nutall, a "presumpuous ass" who "deserved the lash" (29 September 1835).
In addition to his quick temper and strong opinions, other aspects of Ord's personality are revealed in the letters. He mistrusted paper money and believed that the United States bank had "probably committed more frauds, and has been the occasion of more mischief and suffering, than any similar corporation that ever was erected." Although at times mistrustful, Ord was generally optimistic about emerging technologies, such as photography, steam-power, and telegraphic communication, feeling that he lived "in an age of wonders."
Many of the letters discuss Ord's feelings on everyday matters and many of the issues that concerned ornithologists of the day, such as the description of rattlesnakes and avian taxonomy. Most of the material relating to his membership at the APS and the ANS are found not in his correspondence to Waterton but in the correspondence from various individuals.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ord's correspondence with Charles Waterton was acquired in 1942 and 1975. Other letters to and from Ord have been acquired from miscellaneous sources..
Related Archival Materials note
Ord appears as a correspondent in a number of manuscript collections at the APS including the papers of John Lawrence Le Conte, Charles Waterton, Isaac Hays, John Torrey, William Darlington and the Peale-Sellers Family correspondence. As a member of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, Ord also appears in the Library Committee records of that collection.
The APS also houses a collection of the Papers of Charles Waterton and family.
Bibliography
Robert McCracken Peck, "George Ord," American National Biography 16 (1999): 755-756.
Naval History Note
The Ord Collection contains a few items which may be of interest to naval historians:
Wilkes, Charles, 1798-1877. United States Exploring Expedition (1838-1842).
Ord, George. Letter to Charles Waterton. 1838 March 27. Bartram's garden. Expedition for the purpose of exploring the South Seas (Wilkes), the United States Exploring Expedition. Peale's museum. 4 pages.
Ord, George. Letter to Charles Waterton. 1842 November 21. Concerning Audubon, Titian R. Peale, and the Wilkes Expedition (the United States Exploring Expedition), Smithsonian Institution and Charles Lucien Bonaparte. 3 pages.
Ord, George. Letter to Charles Waterton. 1844 August 25. Packets from Petty Vaughan for the American Philosophical Society. Mentions magnetic telegraph; Captain Wilkes' narrative of the United States Exploring Expedition. 3 pages.
Ord, George. Letter to Charles Waterton. 1845 June 22. Peale's museum in hands of scheriff. Narrative of the United States Exploring Expedition. Visits from Audubon; his works. Copy of Audubon's Birds for the American Philosophical Society. 4 pages.
Early American History Note
The collection of George Ord correspondence is a relatively small but significant collection. Most of the letters are from George Ord to Charles Waterton, a British naturalist, and reflect their shared interest in natural history, especially ornithology. The letters deal with Ord’s rivalry with Audubon. Many of Ord's letters question the accuracy of Audobon’s work. Other letters touch on Alexander Wilson and on new techniques for capturing images of animal life, such as the use of the Daguerre process.
The letters also discuss aspects of nineteenth century society. Mention is made of Peale’s Museum (the Philadelphia Museum). One letter contains a detailed description of the museum’s new quarters in 1838, another in 1854 describes its destruction. Other letters discuss the economy (including the California Gold Rush), politics (especially the election of James K. Polk and the Mexican-American War), and APS business. Ord also mentions Thomas Nuttall (described as a “presumptuous ass”), whose travel journal from 1810 the APS has. The collection contains a detailed description of many letters’ content.
Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia.; American Philosophical Society.; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867; Biddle, Alexander, 1819-1899; Bonaparte, Charles Lucian, 1803-1857; British Association for the Advancement of Science.; Brown, David Paul, 1795-1872; Brown, John, 1800-1859; Darlington, William, 1781-1863; Du Chaillu, Paul B., (Paul Belloni), 1835-1903; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844; Garibaldi, Guiseppe, 1807-1882; Gray, John Edward, 1800-1875; Herrick, E. C.; Humphreys, A. A., (Andrew Atkinson), 1810-1883; Hunter, John Dunn, 1798?-1827.; Jardine, William, Sir, 1800-1874; Kane, Paul, 1810-1871; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870; National Gallery of Art (U.S.); National Institute for the Promotion of Science; Nuttall, Thomas, 1786-1859; Peale's Museum (Philadelphia, Pa.).; Peale, Titian Ramsay, 1799-1885; Philological Society (Great Britain); Raleigh, Walter, Sir, 1552?-1618.; Roux de Rochelle, 1762-1849; Royal Society (Great Britain).; Sartori, John B.; Smithsonian Institution.; St. Paul's Church (Philadelphia, Pa.); Stout Family; Tidyman, Philip, d. 1850; Vaughan, William; Wagner, Tobias; Waterton, Charles, 1782-1865; Wied, Maximilian, Prinz von, 1782-1867; Wilkes, Charles, 1798-1872; Abolitionists--United States--Attitudes; Animals--Habits and behavior of; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851. Birds of America; Banks and banking -- United States.; Birds--Study and teaching; Birds.; Cholic Acid; Church buildings--Pennsylvania-Philadelphia; Cicada (Genus); Columbidia; Cuba--Insurrection, 1849-1851; Cuckoos; Daguerreotypes; Dictionary of the English language. Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784; Dove; Early National Politics; English language--Dictionaries; Exploration.; Famines--Ireland; France--19th Century; Frogs--United States; Frost--Great Britain; Geese; General Correspondence; Gold mines and mining--California--19th Century; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Russia; Harpers Ferry (W. Va.)--History--John Brown's Raid, 1859; Heatstroke; Immigrants--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Influenza--United States; Irish--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Italy--Revolution of 1848; Italy--War of 1859; Kagoshima-shi (Japan); Memorials--Great Britain; Mercury; Mexican War, 1846-1848; Monk, Maria, d. 1850; Natural History; Partridges; Peale, Charles Willson, 1741-1827--Art collections.; Philadelphia History; Potatoes; Railroads--19th Century; Rattlesnake; Religion; Reptiles; Russia--Foreign relations--Germany-Prussia; Science and Technology; Scientific Correspondence; Sea monsters; Secession--Southern States; Skin--Diseases-Treatment; Slaves--Emancipation-America; Smoking--Health aspects--United States; Soap trade--Pennsylvania; Steam-navigation--Atlantic Ocean; Steamboat disasters; Stowe, Harriet Beecher, 1811-1896 Uncle Tom's Cabin.; Telegraph; United States Exploring Expedition (1838-1842).; United States--Civil War 1861 1865--Participation Foreign; United States--Civil War, 1861-1865; United States--Civil War, 1861-1865--Economic aspects; United States--Politics and government--1861-1865; United States. President (1861-1865: Lincoln).; Wilkes, Charles, 1798-1872. Narrative of the United States exploring expedition.; Williams, Eleazer, 1787-1858
- Papers
  - Comments on Audubon's book [Birds of America], July 20, 1831; 9x7-1/2; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Scope and Contents note
    Walton Hall, A.D.S. 4p.,end.in pencil. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence). Formerly B Or2.1. Concerning Audubon and Wilson, and Audubon's attempt to become a member of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, July 24, 1831; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Brief letter mentioning Mr. Naylor.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, April 23, 1832; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    [Phila.,] A.L.S. 3p. and add. (inc. - begins on p.9) Criticism of Audubon and his work. Arrival of Titian Peale, with rich cargo of the natural productions of the South. Duke of Sussex elected to membership in A.P.S.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], April 23, 1832; 10x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L. 8p. Incomplete. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Birds. Audubon on the rattlesnake, vultures, bald eagle, and Birds of America Refers to Charles Bonaparte and Titian Peale study of the bald eagle.
    General note
    not located 4/2010
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, April 28, 1833; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Buckingham, Bucks, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Criticism of Audubon and his work; mentions also Alexander Wilson, Cuvier, Dr. Jones.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], July 16, 1834; 10x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Buckingham, Penna., A.L. 4p. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Concerning sea-serpents, whales and snakes. Refers to Silliman and his journal and Jacob Bigelow.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Sept. 17, 1834; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Buckingham, A.L.S. 4p., add. Ring doves; humming birds. Mentions Audubon.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Nov. 15, 1834; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Mentions Mr. Vaughan of the Philosophical society, Prof. Jameson, Dr. Harlan, Hays, Titian Peale, Audubon, Harrison Hall, Nuttall, Maclure, Lesueur; death of Mr. Say.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, March 16, 1835; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Buckingham, A.L. 4p., add. Cold weather. Egg laying. Catholicism.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], April 15, 16, 17, 1835; 10x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Buckingham, Penna., A.L.S. 12p.end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Concerning Audubon, his reputation in England, Birds of America,especially the raven. Refers to rattlesnakes and fangs, T.R.Peale, eagles, hawks, Jameson. Expulsion from vice-presidency of ANS by Harlan et al, over his eulogy of Say read before APS.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], Sept. 29, 1835; 10x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Buckingham,Penna., A.L. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Concerning the ornithological works of Audubon, Nuttall and Wilson. His work on the cow bunting. Has been building on his home. Refers to the APS.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], March 25, 1838; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L. 4p. Incomplete. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Comments on religion. Concerning Waterton's popularity in the U.S.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, March 27, 1838; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Bartram's garden. Expedition for the purpose of exploring the South Seas (Wilkes). Peale's museum.
  - Letter to [Charles Bonaparte;], Sept. 10, 1841; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., Copy of A.L. In French. Transcribed in letter from Ord to Charles Waterton, Sept. 18, 1841.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Sept. 18, 1841; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Noble conduct of Charles Bonaparte; transcribes letter sent to him on the 10th inst. Paintings sent to Petty Vaughan to be sold.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Sept. 30, 1841; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Disposition of paintings sent to Petty Vaughan. Daguerre process; Mr. Cornelius of Philadelphia. Audubon's work. Ord's article vindicating Wilson from the aspersions of Audubon. Mr. Tyler and bank.
  - Letter to George Ord, March 17, 1842; Herrick, E. C.
    On behalf of Benjamin Silliman. Asks to have papers forwarded to Silliman in New York.
  - Letter to George Ord, July 6, 1842; Vaughan, William, 1752-1850
    London. Regarding APS publications. Refers to Ch. Biddle and bank.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Wakefield, Eng., Nov. 21, 1842; 10x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, Typed L. 3p. Copy. (from original in possession (1968) of R.Milnes Walker, Wergs Copse, Kintbury, Newbury, Berks.) Formerly B Or2.1. Concerning Audubon, T.R.Peale and the Wilkes Expedition, Smithsonian Institution and Charles Lucien Bonaparte.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Dec. 25, Dec. 27, 1841; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Ord's paper on the tortoise. Bank situation in the U.S. Last illness of [John Vaughan ?].
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, March 17, 18, 1842; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p., add. Failure of the Bank of the U.S.;many suicides resulting. Death of John Vaughan; Ord his successor as librarian and treasurer of th A.P.S.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Feb. 5, 1843; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    In French. Extract of letter written to Charles Bonaparte. Discusses political situation; refers to Geological society, Academy of Natural Sciences, APS, and Franklin Institute.
  - Letter to George Ord, March 14, 1843; Peale, Titian Ramsay, 1799-1885
    Refers to lack of support for completion of late expedition. Many specimens are missing. Expects to be penniless soon. Asks about Society and Museum.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Aug. 23, 1843; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 4p.,add. Audubon's work on the quadrupeds. Positive view of inventions. Mentions Dr. Bachman; the A.P.S. Sale of building housing Peale's museum.
  - Letter to George Ord, Jan. 13, 1844; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
    Refers to Roux de Rochelle’s letter and donation of a book.
  - Letter to [Charles Waterton], Feb. 24, 1844; 10x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ord-Waterton correspondence.) Formerly B Or2.1. Concerning Audubon's Birds and Quadrupeds. Olfactory nerves of buzzards, with comments on Audubon by Smith, Pollock, Owen, and Bachman. Refers to APS and William Jardine. Refers to Yarrell and Audubon.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Aug. 25, 1844; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L.S. 3p. and add. Packets from Petty Vaughan for A.P.S. Mentions magnetic telegraph. Capt. Wilkes' Narrative of the Exploring Expedition.
  - Letter to George Ord, Sept. 30, 1844; Wagner, Tobias
    Regarding a meeting of the British Association in London. Reports on several lectures, including by Lyell, Liebig, and Rope.
  - Letter to George Ord, Nov. 26, 1844; Peale, Titian Ramsay, 1799-1885
    Dislikes his job, poorly paid, is painting his new birds and animals in oil.
  - Letter to Titian Ramsey Peale, Dec. 4, 1844; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Will use influence at Peale’s behalf. Mentions Kane and Dr. Patterson. Peale’s best friends are attached to the party that has lately won the presidency.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    Copy. Orig. at HSP.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, June 22, 1845; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Phila., A.L. 4p., add. Peale's museum in hands of sheriff. Narrative of the Exploring Expedition. Visits from Audubon; his works. Copy of Audubon's Birds for A.P.S.
  - Letter to George Ord, Feb. 16, 1845; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    Refers to Patterson, Kane and Nulty.
  - Letter to George Ord, April 7, 1845; Peale, Titian Ramsay, 1799-1885
    Letter of introduction for the botanist William Rich, Esq. who would like to consult botany libraries in Philadelphia.
  - Letter to Charles Waterton, Aug. 23, 1845; 8" x 10"; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p., add. Letter from the Prince of Canino. Pennsylvania state debt.
  - Letter to George Ord, May 20, 1845; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
    Note asking Ord to deliver a copy of Dobson’s Encyclopedia to the Franklin Institute.